<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The iust censure and reproofe of Martin Iunior. Wherein the rash and vndiscreete headines of the foolish youth, is sharply mette with, and the boy hath his lesson taught him, I warrant you, by his reuerend and elder brother, Martin Senior, sonne and heire vnto the renowmed Martin Mar-prelate the Great. Where also, least the springall shold be vtterly discouraged in his good meaning, you shall finde, that hee is not bereaued of his due commendations</title>
            <author>Marprelate, Martin, pseud.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1589</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07041</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17458</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112313</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847568</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847568</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12606</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07041)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12606)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 433:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The iust censure and reproofe of Martin Iunior. Wherein the rash and vndiscreete headines of the foolish youth, is sharply mette with, and the boy hath his lesson taught him, I warrant you, by his reuerend and elder brother, Martin Senior, sonne and heire vnto the renowmed Martin Mar-prelate the Great. Where also, least the springall shold be vtterly discouraged in his good meaning, you shall finde, that hee is not bereaued of his due commendations</title>
                  <author>Marprelate, Martin, pseud.</author>
                  <author>Throckmorton, Job, 1545-1601, attributed name.</author>
                  <author>Penry, John, 1559-1593, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Hodgkins,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Wolston, Warks.? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>29 July 1589]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Martin Senior = Martin Marprelate, who has been identified with John Penry and, more probably, with Job Throckmorton.</note>
                  <note>Often referred to as "Martin Senior".</note>
                  <note>On the two title pages seen (Huntington and Lambeth) the space after "Mar-prelate" in line 9 of the title has slipped under the forme; the letters "prelate" are very heavily printed and some of the surrounding type has failed to print.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁴.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The reproofe of Martin Iunior.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Marprelate controversy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12606:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12606:1"/>
            <p>The iuſt cenſure and reproofe of Martin Iunior.</p>
            <p>Wherein the rash and vndiſcreete hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines of the foolish youth, is sharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mette with, and the boy hath his leſson taught him, I warrant you, by his reuerend and elder brother, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin Senior, ſonne and heire vnto the renowmed Martin Mar-prelate he Great.</p>
            <p>Where alſo, leaſt the ſpringall ſhold be vtterly diſcouraged in his good meaning, you ſhall finde, that hee is not bereaued of his due commendations.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:12606:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12606:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The reproofe of Martin Iunior, by his elder brother.</head>
            <p>WHo then! And boyes will now be a Piſtle-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, either without their fathers leaue, or their elder brothers aduiſe, we ſhall haue our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Art brought to a prettie paſſe within a while, I could a told tis long agoe, that my father would get him ſo many ſons, as Iohn Canturbury woulde haue no cauſe to ſitte quiet at dinner or ſupper, for looking to his young nephewes. I thought boyes would be a doing. But, fooliſh ſtripling, canſt thou tell what thou haſt done? I weene not, if my father ſhould be hurt, either at the Groine, or at the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbes of Lisbone, is this the way either to cure him, or to comforte him, to publiſhe his ſcrabled and weather-beaten papers in this forte? What if hee hadde in purpoſe to write no more, ſeeing the daunger and trouble that comes of it? Will this be any meanes to worke the olde mans quietnes, for a fooliſh and a headie ſpringal, to go ſet abroad his papers? Thou ſaweſt wel enough, that Martins doings were now almoſt forgot &amp; huiſht. And the<note n="a" place="margin">Beare wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, Reader, that I giue my Lordes their right titles.</note> men of ſinne themſelues, I meane the Cantur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burie Caiphas, with the reſt of his Antichriſtian beaſts, who beare his abominable marke, were content in a maner to turne his purpoſes from a ſerious matter, to a point of jeſting, wherewith they would haue onely rimers and ſtage-players (that is, plaine rogues, as thou haſt well noted) to
<pb facs="tcp:12606:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>deale. So that had not thy vntimely folly bewray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it ſelfe, it may be, that the ſyllogiſmes whereby our father hath crackt the crowne of Canturbury, ſhould haue had no other anſwere, or he himſelfe none other puniſhment but this. I faith lette him go, Martin is a madde knaue. Whereas now vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon this ſcrabbling and paltring of thine, marke whether Iohn Canturburie will not ſende for all the knaue purſuvants that belongs vnto his pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and ſet them a worke with the confutation of Martin, vſing ſome ſuch ſpeach as this is, in the direction of them, for the choice of their Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments againſt him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">An Oration of Iohn Can turburie to the purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, when he directeth his warrants vnto them to poſt after Martin.</note>Now ſirs, is not her Majeſties high commiſſion, and my ſelfe alſo being the chiefe thereof, and one of her Majeſties priuie counſell wel ſet vp, with a company of meſſengers, as long as we haue you to goe of our buſines? What thinke you? Haue you beene carefull of vs and our places, to ſinde vs out the preſſe and letters, wherewith theſe ſeditious Martins are printed? Or, haue you diligently ſoght mee out Walde-graue the Printer, Newman the Cobler, Sharpe the booke binder of Northamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, and that ſeditious Welch man Penry, who you ſhall ſee will prooue the Author of all theſe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belles? I thanke you Maiſter Munday, you are a good Gentleman of your worde. Ah thou Iudar, thou that haſt alreadie betrayed the Papiſtes, I thinke meaneſt to betray vs alſo, Diddeſt thou not aſſure me, without all doubt, that thou wouldeſt bring mee in, Penry, Newman, Walde-graue, preſſe, letters, and all, before Saint Andrewes day laſt. And nowe thou ſeeſt we are as farre to ſeeke for them, as euer we were. Nay, vnleſſe we haue
<pb facs="tcp:12606:3"/>them now, they are like to trouble<note n="a" place="margin">But not the church of Chriſt good vncle: you doe not ſo great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eare though they did.</note> our Churche more then euer they did. For here is a yong Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin hatched out of ſome poyſoned egge of that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious libeller, Old Martin. Why truly it grieues me, at the heart, that I, by her Maieſties fauor, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing more authoritie in mine hande to repreſſe theſe Puritanes, then any biſhop elſe hath had in England theſe thirtie yeeres, yet ſhoulde be more troubled and moleſted by them theſe ſixe yeeres, then all my predeceſſors haue beene theſe ſix and twentie yeeres. And all this commeth by reaſon of your vnfaithfulnes and negligence, whome wee ſend for them. Well, I giue you warning, looke better vnto your offices, or elſe let mee be dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned body and ſoule,<note n="b" place="margin">Neuer conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter man, for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, thou arte ſure of that alreadie.</note> if I turne you not all out of your places. Therefore looke to it: for nowe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one of you ſhal haue warrants, both for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and as many as you will ſubſtitute vnder you beſides. Bring vs whomeſoeuer you ſuſpect, your warrants ſhall ſerue you to doe it. And if you can ſinde vs eyther young or olde Martin, Penry, or Walde-graue, ſo that you bring the preſſe and let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, hee ſhall haue fortie poundes for his labour, who ſo euer will bring them, his charges and all bonie cleare. But if you bring vs neither Martin, the preſſe, nor thoſe aforenamed, neuer looke vs in the face more. And me thinkes for your owne good, you ſhoulde be carefull to get in theſe ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous men: for if we that are Lordes of the Cleargie go downe once, then ſhall you be ſure to fall: for, poore men, you haue nothing but what you get in<note n="c" place="margin">And you haue nothing neither your ſelues, but what you get in the ſeruice of your Lorde and Maſter the diuel.</note> our ſeruice that are your Lordes and Maiſters. And me thinkes, if theſe wayward men had anie conſcience in them, they woulde not ſeeke our o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowe
<pb facs="tcp:12606:4"/>with tooth and naile, as they doe, ſeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo many honeſt poore men, yea, and manie a good Gentleman too by my troth, liue onely by vs and our places.</p>
            <p>Well, if euer you meane to do anie good in this matter, take mee this courſe, which wee here in commiſſion haue thought meeteſt; let a ſix or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of you, or your ſubſtitutes that ſtay heere in London, watch mee Paules Churchyard, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally haue an eie to Boyles ſhop at the Roſe. And let ſome one or two of you that are vnknowen goe in thither, and if there be any ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers in the ſhop, fall in talke with them of Martin, commend him, and eſpecially his ſonnes laſt libell, (and heere, hee that will take that courſe, take me this, that if need be you may ſhew it) ſhewing, that by great friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe you gote one of them, ſaying alſo, that you vnderſtoode a man might there helpe his friend to ſome, if he were acquainted with Maſter Boyle, and offer largely for it. Now ſir, if any ſhall either enter with you vnto any ſpeches againſt the ſtate, and in defence of theſe libelles: or elſe, if any can procure you to the ſight of the bookes, be ſure to bring them before vs. Though you learne not their names, yet your warrants ſhall ſerue your turnes, in as much as you doe ſuſpect them. And thus I would haue ſome of you beſtowed.</p>
            <p>Let three or foure more of you or your ſubſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes be euery day at the Blacke Friers, Lincolnes inne, White-chappell, Paules chaine, as often as Charke, Gardiner, Egerton, or Cooper do preach. And truely, my Lorde of London, I marueile<note n="a" place="margin">Surelie nuncle I dare ſweare for him he is not in the fault: for they ſtand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his will.</note> you ſuffer theſe men all this while, to trouble the ſtate by their preachings: by the maſſe I had not thoght
<pb facs="tcp:12606:4"/>they ſhould haue ſtoode halfe this time) and there ſee if you can drawe by ſpeach anie thing from any Martiniſt, and let vs talke with them. Eſpecially marke if you ſee any before the ſermon beginnes, ſetting their heads together, and whiſpering vnder their cloakes, if you doe, be ſure they are reading Martin, and haue them foorthwith to the priſon vntill we ſend for them, or cauſe them to putte in ſufficient ſureties, to appeare the next court day.</p>
            <p>You that ſtay here in London, muſt alſo be ſure, if poſſibly you can, to haue a watch at al common innes, to ſee what carriage of paper, and other ſtuffe, either goes from, or commes to London. Thereby you may happely learne ſomething. And marke if any Puritane receiueth any thing, open his packe, that you may be ſure hee hath no Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tins ſent him. We will direct our warrants ſo, that you may ſearch all packes<note n="a" place="margin">I hope the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuvants in time ſhall be able to make a good li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, in taking toll of thoſe packes which they do not open</note> at your diſcretion. We will take order alſo, that the Court may be watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed who diſperſe, or reade theſe libelles there. And in faith I thinke they doe my Lord of Eſſex greate wrong, that ſay, he fauours Martin: I do not think he will be ſo vnwiſe, as to fauour theſe, who are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies vnto the ſtate. For if hee doe, her Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, I can tell him, will withdraw her gratious fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour from him; but take you no care for the court. Watch you London, and learne mee where New-man and Walde-graues haunt is, and there be ſure to watch earely and late. Haue an eie alſo vnto all the Puritanes houſes in London, eſpecially my L. Maiors, Alderman Martins, and the Preachers houſes. Let none that you ſuſpect be vncited.</p>
            <p>As for you that goe into the countrey, I woulde haue ye eſpecialy go into Northampton and War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicke
<pb facs="tcp:12606:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſhires, and command the Maior, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtables of Northampton to keepe watch and warde for Sharpe and Penry, and if they can take them, let them bring them vp, and we wil be ſure to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent them well for their paines. Others muſt goe into Eſſex, Suffolke, and Norffolke. And if you can bring vs no Martiniſts from thence (at the leaſt, that by that meanes your charges may be borne, I would ye might ſtarue for me.) There is Moore, there is Aline, there is Knewſtub, there is Wright, with many others, all very ſeditious men, that is pitty by my troth, that ſo many worſhipfull and good nurtured knights and gentlemen, are carried away with them, and their way wardnes, as in thoſe partes are ſeduced. But I hope her Majeſtie will haue an vniformitie. To be briefe, I haue ſaide e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough vnto you alreadie, but my meaning is, that you ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> her Majeſtie hath, or finde out Martin. Goe me to Deuonſhire, and to the North partes, where my Lords grace of Yorke alſo will direct his warrants by you, to ſeeke this traitour Martin. For I will haue him, or elſe I wil no longer be archbiſhop of Canturbutie. He die at the Groine, as they ſaie? Naie, heele be hanged ere heele die there. He is in ſome corner of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, lurking and doing miſchiefe. I tel you true, I<note n="a" place="margin">He beleeue you o your word</note> doe thinke him and his brood to be worſe then the Ieſuits. Theſe Martiniſts are all of<note n="b" place="margin">Sauing your reuerence vncle Cantur. you lie in your throate.</note> them trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and enemies vnto her Majeſtie, they will o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowe the ſtate, they are moſt rebellious and diſobedient vnto all good proceedings. No war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning will ſerue them, they growe worſe and worſe. I perſwaded my ſelfe, that none euer durſt attempt to write beſides this deſperate wretch Martin him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,
<pb facs="tcp:12606:5"/>if he ſtill enjoy his libertie, his broode wil be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as deſperate as himſelfe, his impunitie will make them preſume to ſpeake againſt the ſtate. And therefore, either get him, or wee ſhall neuer ſtaie their courſe. And I thinke I ſhall grow ſtarke <hi rend="sup">a</hi> madde with you, vnleſſe you bring him.<note place="margin">Amen, good Iohn, if thou doeſt not be long to the Lord, ka M. Martin Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior.</note> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, my maiſters, as you haue anie care for the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifieng of the ſtate, and your owne preferrement, ſome waie or other compaſſe mee to finde the firſt Martin himſelfe whereſoeuer hee bee. Spare no charges. Get him, and ſee what weele do for you. For if we were not in hope to come by him throgh your meanes, we woulde caſt about another waie, to ſuppreſſe his libelling. For wee woulde make friendes to haue him proclamed traitour, and haue it fellonie, if wee coulde, for anie manne to reade his writings. And heere an ende with you.</p>
            <p>Loe, ſir boy, haue you not ſpunne a faire threed, for our fathers eaſe and quietneſſe, and for the quietneſſe of your brethren? If our vncle Cantur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burie ſhould take this courſe, where ſhall the old man ſtaie then? You ſee England wil be made too hore for him, if hee be liuing. Whie thou ſimple and vnexperienced ladde, thou, my father, my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I tell thee had beene better, it maie bee, that thou haddeſt neuer, I tell thee trueth, learned a worde of Iriſh in thy life, then to haue in this heate of the yeare publiſhed his vnperfite queſtions. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thou not ſee, thy vncle Canturburie abroad in his viſitation? Doeſt thou not ſee with how manie men Eſau rides, that if hee meete with his poore brother Iacob, he maie be ſure to ſucke his blood. Is ſeuen ſcore horſe nothing, thinkeſt thou, to bee in the traine of an Engliſh Prieſt? whereof alſo
<pb facs="tcp:12606:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>there are thirtie Golde chaines? Doeſt thou thinke, that the kingdome of Chriſt which thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeeketh to builde ſhall be able to ſtand, ſeeing Iohn Canturburie, with ſo manie menne rideth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the countrie, to proclame nothing elſe but fire and ſworde, vnto as manie as profeſſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to be the true ſubjects thereof? Whie thou ſeeſt he goes a viſiting purpoſlie for no other end, but to make it knowen, what an enmitie and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred hee beareth to the Goſpell and kingdome of Chriſt Ieſus, and to ſhew howe carefull he is, that that hereſie of preaching maie not preuaile. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thou then perſwade thy ſelfe, ſeelie ſtripling, that there is anie good to be done, in ſending a Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle vnto him, ſeeing he hath ſo man e men in his traine who will ſweare for him, that he loues none of theſe hote preachers. Mee thinkes my father himſelfe ſhoulde be afraide of him, beeing ſo well horſed as he is. And therefore follie for one of his young ſonnes, to thinke his ſtrength ſufficient to beare the encounter.</p>
            <p>It may be thou wilt ſay, that thy father is euerie day in the weeke able to make as many men of his owne charges; I woulde he were elſe: if hee be, it is more then I knowe, I promiſe thee, and I thinke more then thou canſt prooue. But howſoeuer it goes, thou ſeeſt what a credite it is for an Engliſh Prieſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to haue ſo many men following of him, as in the day of judgement there may be enough, of thoſe that ware his liuerie, to witnes againſt him, that in this life he was a monſtrous Antichriſtian pope, and a moſt bloody oppreſſor of Gods Saints.</p>
            <p>Be it, my father were dead, as you ſeeme to giue out, and for mine owne parte, I will not gaineſay
<pb facs="tcp:12606:6"/>you, becauſe I for my parte maie truelie ſaie, that his eldeſt childe neuer knewe him, and therefore is ignorant whether he be liuing or dead: yet bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Martin, I doe ſee in the publiſhing of theſe things by you, two great ſlippes committed; the one of inconſideracie, the other of vnduetifulnes. Your raſhnes, and want of wiſedome other men, I ſee are like to feele, your vnduetifulnes is onelie towardes my ſelfe, which I cannot well put vp, and becauſe of thy raſhnes.</p>
            <p>Marke whether thoſe poore men beforenamed, to wit, Penry, Sharpe, Walde graue, Newman, &amp;c. with many other good men, who <hi>I</hi> dare ſware for them, did neuer medle nor make at anie time, with the metropoliticall writings of our renowmed fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſhal not be now as hotlie purſued after, as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they were. And al this comes of thy fooliſh and paltrie meddling in matters too high for thy capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie. And thus other men are like to ſmart by thy follie.</p>
            <p>As for my ſelfe, to omitte the honourable men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that my father (my father, I ſaie, <hi>Quem honoris cauſa nomino, quoties nomino, nomino autem ſaepiſſime</hi>) made of me in his writings, whereas hee did not once vouchſafe to ſpeake a worde of ſuch a dilling as thou art, <hi>I</hi> ſhould haue thought, that the verie name of an elder brother ſhold haue taught thee, that there had beene one in the world, to whome by right of inheritance, the Piſtling of biſhops had belonged, after the deceaſe of reuerend Martin himſelfe. Whie who ſhould ſette out my fathers writings but <hi>I,</hi> Martin Senior, his ſonne? At the leaſt, who ſhould publiſh them without my leaue? So that herein thy vndutifulnes is no leſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy
<pb facs="tcp:12606:7"/>headie and raſh inconſideracie.</p>
            <p>To retourne againe vnto our reuerend father. Of all other things <hi>I</hi> would wiſh thee not to come within his reach, if hee be liuing, for an thou do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, <hi>I</hi> can tell thee heele giue thee ſuch a leſſon for thy ſaweineſſe, as <hi>I</hi> thinke thou ſhalt neuer be Lord biſhop while thou liueſt. For it may bee, that the expectation which menne haue conceiued of the proofe of ſuch points,<note place="margin">My father, I tell you, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing his wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhip, ſtandes vpon the cre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dit o his children.</note> as thou haſt laid downe, will force him to alter his purpoſe in, More worke for the Cooper, and fall a proouing of theſe thinges, leaſt men ſhould hold themſelues deluded by thee. And will this be no paine thinke you, ſir boy? Will it be no labour for a man, hauing finiſhed a booke, to alter his courſe, and make it wholie newe? And this thou knoweſt he muſt do, vnleſſe his wiſedom hath before hand preuented the inconuenience. <hi>I</hi> deny not in deede, but it is eaſier for him to alter his courſe, then for any one writer that <hi>I</hi> knowe of, becauſe hee hath choſen him ſuch a methode as no man elſe beſides hath done. Nay, his ſyllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſmes, exiomes, method, and all are of his owne making, hee will borrowe none of theſe common ſchoole rules, no not ſo much as the common gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar, as it apeareth by that excellent point of poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, written in Latin by him againſt Doctor Wing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken de Werd.<note place="margin">D. Prime.</note> There thou ſhalt ſee ſuch grammar, ſuch Arte, ſuch wit and conueiance of matter, as for the varietie of the learning, and the pleaſaunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the ſtile, the like is not elſe-where to bee found.</p>
            <p>But leaſt I ſhould vtterly diſcourage thee poore knaue, <hi>I</hi> will before <hi>I</hi> touch the reſt of thine ouer ſights, attribute vnto thee thy deſerued common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations.
<pb facs="tcp:12606:7"/>
               <hi>I</hi> confeſſe then, that thou canſt doe pren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily well; thou canſt enter reaſonablie into the ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nows of thine vncle Canturburies popedome, and make a tollerable Anatomie thereof. <hi>I</hi> muſt needs alſo ſay for thee, Iacke, that thou feareſt none of theſe popes. And <hi>I</hi> promiſe thee, <hi>I</hi> thinke thou haſt a pretie mother wit of thine owne; but, poore boy, thou wanteſt wiſedome, withall to gouerne thy witte. Thou wanteſt that which thine vncka Brid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges hath not, that is, wiſdome to direct thee in the carriage of thoſe pretie crochets that thou haſt in thy head. And the poore old Drone o Sarum lacks that altogether, wherewith thou arte prettily fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, viz. a naturall wit. Neither doe I deny, boy, but that thou art Tom tell-troth, euen like thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and that thou canſt not abide, to ſpeake vnto thine vnckle Cantur. by circumloquutions and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphraſes, but ſimply and plainely thou breakeſt thy minde vnto him, and telleſt him vnto his face, without al theſe friuolous circumſtances of, What is your name? and, Who gaue you that name? of, Ant pleaſe your worſhippe, &amp;c. Thou telleſt him plainelie to his face, I ſay, that he is a very Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian beaſt, and an intollerable oppreſſour of Gods Church. And mee thought, when I read that point in thy Epilogue: then thought I, it will prooue a vengeable boy in time. For mee thinks that already, <hi>patrizat ſat bene certe.</hi> And truſt mee Iacke, I commend thee for thy plaineneſſe. And doe ſo ſtill, boy, for trueth neuer ſhames the Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter I warrant thee, and take it o my word. For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed thine vncle Cantur. is no leſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a moſt vile and curſſed tyrant in the Church. And a plain An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt he is euen by the doctrine of the Church
<pb facs="tcp:12606:8"/>of England, and ſo by the doctrine of our Church are the reſt of our curſſed biſhops, in the proofe of which point by and by I will a little inſiſt. And becauſe manie take ſnuffe, that my father ſhoulde account them, yea, and prooue them petrie Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts, I will manifeſtlie prooue them to be ſo, e<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen by the doctrine of the Church of Englande, maintained by ſtatute and her Majeſties roiall pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledge. For my father now hath taught vs ſuche a waie to reaſon againſt theſe Caiphaſes, in the Theſes ſet downe by thee, as wil anger al the vains in Iohn Canturburies heart. And that is, to ſhew, that they are ennemies vnto the doctrine of our church. Vnto the point I will come anone. But, firſt, brother Martin, I will ſchoole you in a pointe or two for your learning, in theſe things wherein I finde your Epilogue to be vnperfite. Firſt then, I trow, I woulde haue had ſome other manner of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations againſt our Puritans for their ſlackenes, then wherwith you haue charged them, as preſent<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly I will declare. Secondlie, I would haue propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſome things of mine own againſt our biſhops, or elſe it ſhoulde haue coſt mee a fall. And that ſhould haue beene after this, or the like ſort:</p>
            <p>I Martin Senior Gentleman, ſonne and heire to the reuerende and woorthie Metropolitane Martin Mar-prelate the Great, doe proteſt, affirme, ſay, propou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, and object againſt Iohn Canturburie and his brethren, in maner and forme following;</p>
            <p>Firſt I proteſt and affirme, that the foreſaide Iohn Whitgift, <hi>alias</hi> Canturburie, which nameth
<pb facs="tcp:12606:8"/>himſelfe archbiſhop of Canturburie, is no Miniſter at all in the church of God, but hath, and doeth wrongfully vſurp, and inuade the name and ſeate of the miniſterie, vnto the great detriment of the Church of God, the vtter ſpoyle of the ſoules of men, &amp; the likelie ruine of this common-wealth, together with the great diſhonour of her Majeſtie and the ſtate. And in this caſe do I affirme al the Lord biſhops in England to be.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Item I do proteſt, that the entering in of this curſſed man Iohn Whitgift, and of all others our biſhoppes in Englande, is not an entring into the church of God by the doore Chriſt Ieſus. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I affirme all of them to be theeues, robbers, wolues, and worriers of the flocke, and therefore no true ſhepeheards.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Item I do proclame the ſaide Iohn Cantur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burie, with the reſt of our Prelates, to bee common ſimoniarkes, ſuch as make merchandize of church liuings and benefices, by faculties, diſpenſations, &amp;c. and make as common a gaine of Church cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, by abſolutions &amp; commutations of pena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp;c. as anie men in the lande doe of their lawefull trades and occupations.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Item I do propound and affirme, that the ſaid Iohn Canturburie and his brethren, do hinder and lette with all their might, the true knowledge of God amongeſt her Majeſties louing ſubjectes, the inhabitants of this kingdome, and thereby, beſides their owne fore-prouided damnation, are guiltie of the blood of infinite thouſands.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Item I doe proclaime, that the ſaide Iohn Whitgift with the reſt of his brethren, doth ſpend and waſte the patrimonie of the Church (which
<pb facs="tcp:12606:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>ought to be employed, in the maintenance of true faithfull Miniſters, and other church vſes) in the perſecuting the true members of Chriſt, her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties moſt truſtie and louing ſubjects, and alſo v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon their owne pompe and ambitious pride, in maintening a rude vngodlie traine of vile men, &amp; a companie of lewde and graceleſſe children.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Item I doe propound, that the ſaid Ioh. Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gift and his brethren, do, as much as in them lieth, ſowe ſedition and diſcontentednes, betweene her Majeſtie, and her true loyall ſubjectes, by preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that their pracriſes in auoiding ſubſcription, and in depriuing men contrarie to lawe, as for the ſurpliſe, denieng to ſubſcribe, &amp;c. is at her Majeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties commandement. As though her Highneſſe would commaund that which were contrarie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the true doctrine of our church, and contrarie vnto her lawfull ſtatutes and priuiledges: Or, as though ſhee woulde ſo delude her louing ſubjects, as publikelie to maintaine that true doctrine, and theſe godlie ſtatutes, which priuately ſhee woulde haue violate and troden vnder feete.</p>
            <p n="7">7 Item I the ſaide Martin Senior, do proteſt and affirme the ſaide Iohn Whitgift, with the reſt of his brethren, to haue incurred the ſtatute of <hi>premunire facies,</hi> for depriuing of Miniſters, for not ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing, not wearing the ſurpliſe, and for other their manifolde proceedings againſt law and equitie.</p>
            <p n="8">8 Item I doe propound all our biſhops for their ſaide practiſes to be, <hi>ipſo facto</hi> depriueable, and that her Majeſtie, if ſhe will doe them but right, may by lawe depriue them al to night before to morrowe.</p>
            <p n="9">9 I do alſo propound and auouch the ſaid Iohn Whitgift, and the reſt of his wicked fraternitie,
<pb facs="tcp:12606:9"/>though by outwarde profeſſion they are in the church, yet to be none of the church, but to haue, vntill they repent and deſire to bee receiued into the church, cut themſelues (by the perſecuting of the trueth, and other their hamous ſinnes) from the church, and ſo without their repentance from the intereſt and inheritance of the kingdom of heauen.</p>
            <p>Item I do proteſt &amp; affirme that the true chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che of God ought to haue no more to do with Io. Canturburie his brother, and their ſynagogue, namely, with their Antichriſtian Courts of facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, &amp;c. with their officers of commiſſaries, arche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacons, chancellors, officialles, dumbe miniſters, &amp;c. then with the ſynagogue of Sathan. And that hee their head and pope, together with his fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaide rabble, are not to bee accounted for that church, whoſe cenſures we are to reuerence and obey, and in the vnitie whereof we are to remaine.</p>
            <p>Item particularly, concerning Iohn Canturbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie himſelfe, I doe affirme, but yet no further then <hi>quatenus probabile,</hi> that is, by great likelihoodes, that he is ſo finally hardened in his hainous ſinnes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God and his church, that as hee cannot be reclaimed, for his mouth is full of curſing againſt God and his Saintes, his feete are ſwift to ſhed the blood of the holie ones, hee teareth in peeces the churches which hee ought to foſter, wilfully pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the ſhepheards from their ſheepe, and ſo ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering them in a moſt lamentable ſorte, making much of wicked men that mainteine his pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and ſmiting the righteous for gaineſaying his wayes, bringing in daily into the church, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by himſelfe or his hang Ions newe errors not
<pb facs="tcp:12606:10"/>heard of before. Blaſpheming the way of trueth. And being rooted in mallice againſt that truth of Chriſt Ieſus (who is bleſſed for euer) which he may ſee, if he did not hood-winke himſelfe, hee with all his power contrarieth and ſtriueth againſt the going forwarde of the Goſpell, leaſt by the light thereof his ſinnes ſhoulde be reprooued. Finally, hee hath in him too too many likelie teſtimonies of an heire of the kingdome of darkeneſſe, where, without his true turning vnto the Lorde, hee ſhall liue in hell for euer.</p>
            <p>And wicked man! if thou meaneſt to bee elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where receiued, that is, into Chriſtes kingdome, turne thee from thy wickednes, and let men and Angelles be witneſſes of thy conuerſion. Thy high place ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not ſaue thee from his wrath whoſe truth thou ſuppreſſeſt, and whoſe members thou doeſt perſecute and impriſon. And I woulde not wiſhe thee to deferre thy repentance, leaſt thou calleſt with the fooliſh virgins when there is no opening. Thou ſeeſt euen heere vpon earth manifeſt tokens of Gods anger towards thee. For thou ſeekeſt for honour; but alas, I know none more contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble then thy ſelfe, the pooreſt faithfull miniſter in the Lord, hath more true reuerence in one day, then thou haſt had ſince the firſt time of thy pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. There are almoſt none of Gods children, but had as lieue ſee a ſerpent, as meete thee, not becauſe they feare thy face, but in as much as it greeueth them, that their eyes are forced to looke vpon ſo wicked an enemie of God and his church. Thine owne creatures them ſelues honour thee, but as tyrants are commonlie honoured of their paraſites and ſycophants. Thy brother the pope
<pb facs="tcp:12606:10"/>hath the like honor vnto thine, that is, an honor whoſe end will be ſhame and confuſion of face for euer. The fearefull and contemptible ende, that haue beene brought vppon many of them, ought to terrifie thee. Nay, the meſſage of death which the Lord ſent lately euen into thine owne houſe, ought to mooue thee, and force thee to confeſſe, that thy yeares alſo, yea, and dayes are nombred. Doctor Perne, thou knoweſt was thy joy, and thou his darling. Hee was the dragon from whoſe ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine breaſts, thou diddeſt firſt drawe this poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, wherewith nowe thou infecteſt the church of God, and feedeſt thy ſelfe vnto damnation. Hee liued a perſecutour, an atheiſt, an hypocrite, and a diſſembler, whome the worlde poynted at, and he died, thou knoweſt, the death due vnto ſuch a life as he ledde; thou knoweſt hee died ſuddenly euen at thine owne palace of Lambehith, when, in thine owne judgement he was likelie, in regarde of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dilie ſtrength, though not of age to out-liue thee. And take thou his death for a forewarning of thy deſtruction, except thou repent.</p>
            <p>And theſe, brother Martin, with ſuch like points, or ſome of thoſe poſitions, wherwith I could haue thwacked my vncles about the ſhoulders I weene, an I had beene in thy place. There is one queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on more which <hi>I</hi> woulde haue propounded for mine vncka Bridges his ſake; O <hi>I</hi> loue him, thou knoweſt. And therefore thus woulde <hi>I</hi> haue ſette downe my proper-ſition on his behalfe:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Martin Senior, Gentleman, doe heere proteſt, affirme, propound, and defend, that if Iohn Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turburie will needs haue a foole in his houſe, wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a wooden dagger, and a cockeſ-combe, that
<pb facs="tcp:12606:11"/>none is ſo fitte for that place as his brother Iohn a Bridges Deane of Sarum. And that he viz. Iohn Bridges is by right to diſplace the other, with who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Lambeth now playes the aſſe, and is him ſelfe to be after a ſolemne maner, according to the booke of ordayning biſhoppes and prieſtes inueſted vnto that roome. Hauing for his officers and daily at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendants theſe gentlemen following. Firſt and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt D. Robert Some for his confeſſor, who alſo, when his maiſter Iohn Sarum hath no vſe of his ſeruice, may be at my Lordes graces commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to reade the <hi>ſtarue-vs</hi> booke in his Chappell at Lambeth. Secondly, if he were not ſomething touched with the coinquinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the fleſh, <hi>I</hi> would appoint none but D. Vnderhill to be his Almoner. Thirdly, Bancroft, and drunken Grauate ſhould be the yeomen of his Cellar. Anderſon<note n="a" place="margin">This chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lein robbed the poore mens box at Northamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton played the Potters part in the morrice daunce, and begotte his maide with child in Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſterſhire: and theſe things hee did ſince he was firſte Prieſt.</note> parſon of Stepney, ſhould make roome before him with his two hand ſtaffe, as he did once before the morrice daunce, at a market towne in the edge of Bucking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham or Bedford ſhires, where he bare the Potters part. His two ſupporters alwayes to leade him by the armes, muſt be ſir Lenard Wright, and ſir Tom Blan o Bedford, the one whereof alſo muſt carrie his bable, and the other a looking glaſſe for their Maiſter, to ſee whether his catercappe doth euety way reach ouer his eares, and ſo ſtand according to his calling. As for Mar-Martin, and Iohn Freg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neuile, they <hi>alterius vicibus,</hi> ſhall be the groomes of his ſtoole. The reſt of his officers <hi>I</hi> referre to the diſcretion of my father, vnto whoſe cenſure alſo <hi>I</hi> doe humbly ſubmit this conceit of mine. And it may be, <hi>I</hi> am bolde, to appoint theſe men their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, who happily are at my fathers direction, to
<pb facs="tcp:12606:11"/>giue their attendance, where hee hath appointed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their places. But this Ile bide by, though my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhoulde ſay nay, that Iohn Bridges deſerues to haue his place that weares the wooden dagger, the cockeſcombe, and the copper chaine at Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>behith. Iſe abide by it, come what wil of the matter.</p>
            <p>The next thing that we are to conſider, brother Martin, is, a more juſt reprehenſion of the Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanes, then that wherewith thou blameſt them. For thou findeſt fault with the Preachers onely, and that juſtly, I confeſſe, becauſe they are no more forward in caſting off theſe our popes. But I ſay, that with more equitie thou mighteſt haue blamed both the gentlemen and people together, with the Miniſters, then the Miniſters alone. For the Miniſters, although they be faultie, yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding thou canſt not denie, but the Gentlemen and people are as deepe in faulte as they are. And I woulde wiſh them both the one &amp; the other, to take this, or ſome ſuch courſe, as I heere ſet downe, which alſo for a great parte of it, though not all, I ſawe in a Puritans hand, and ſo came by a coppie of it, thinking if <hi>I</hi> coulde haue heard of my father, to let him haue the vſe of my copy: but now you ſee I publiſh it my ſelfe. <hi>I</hi> would then haue al the Puritans in the land, both lordes, knights, gentlemen, miniſters, and people, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come joint ſuiters in one ſupplicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie, and the Lords of her honorable priuie coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell in theſe petitions;</p>
            <p n="1">1 Firſt, that there may be a redreſſe of the great ignorance wherewith our whole land is ouergro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen by placing, able, and faithfull teachers ouer euery congregation as neere as may be.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12606:12"/>
            <p n="2">2 Secondly, that al vnlawful and ſinful callings may be remoued out of our miniſterie &amp; church.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Thirdlie, that the church within her Majeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties dominions may bee gouerned by theſe offices and officers onelie, which the Lorde Chriſt Ieſus hath ſet downe in his worde.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Fourthlie, that for the quiet and orderlie ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vp of theſe controuerſies which are riſen in our church, concerning the gouernement and ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies thereof, betweene our Prelates, and thoſe learned men, which are contrary minded vnto them, there might be had a quiet meeting of both the parties, and the controuerſies determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned on their ſide, who ſhall be found to deale for (and not againſt) the trueth: Or, if this fourth pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition cannot take place, I would haue this in the ſteade thereof, viz.</p>
            <p>That it may pleaſe her Majeſtie, and the Lordes of her Majeſties honourable priuie counſell, to ſee that the true ſubjects of this crowne, may not bee troubled, as nowe they are, for defending ſuch points, as being according vnto the word of God, are alſo according to the priuiledged doctrine of the church of England, which is maintened by the ſtatutes of this land, and that in caſe the Prelates doe moleſt any man, as now they doe, for maintei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the doctrine of our church, or otherwiſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary vnto the lawes of our land, it may be lawfull for him or them thus injuried, to haue his reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die at the Kings bench, againſt the ſaide Prelates.</p>
            <p>Nowe Iacke, what ſayeſt thou? I am ſure thou canſt not denie, but theſe petitions, in thy judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment would be an eaſie ſute. I trowe ſo too, and I thinke, that now thou findeſt greater fault, or at
<pb facs="tcp:12606:12"/>the leaſt as great, with the Puritane noblemen, gentlemen, and people, as with the miniſters, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this or the like courſe goeth not on forward. And I can tell thee there would be gotten an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth thouſand hands to this ſupplication, of kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen men in the land, all her Majeſties moſt loyall and truſtie louing ſubjects. Thou mayeſt then well thinke what a ſtroke ſo many woulde ſtrike toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, eſpeciallie in ſo reaſonable and juſt a ſuite. And heereby our biſhoppes ſhoulde be prooued to be Lord biſhoppes in deede, that is,<note n="a" place="margin">A pretie briefe definition of a Lord biſhop.</note> vngodlie and ſlaunderous lyars. When her Majeſtie ſawe, that the Puritanes ſeeke not any intollerable courſe, (for if the foreſaide petitions be not to be borne, I know not what is ſufferable) as the biſhops woulde pretend. And further it ſhould appeare, that they are not a fewe, and of ſmall reputation, but in a maner the ſtrength of our land, and the ſynowe of her Majeſties royall gouernement, which our bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops do falſely note with the names of Puritanes. The conſideration whereof, I tell thee, euen in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie, woulde make, that this their ſuite ſhoulde not be haſtely rejected, eſpecially in ſuch a time, as wherein wee nowe liue in daunger of our enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies abroad, and therefore had neede of no cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of diſcouragement at home. Whie man, this were alſo ſuch a courſe as it would deſcrie our bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops Engliſh, to be plaine ſlaunder and treacherie againſt the trueth, and the mainteiners thereof, as indeede it is.</p>
            <p>The biſhops Engliſh wilt thou ſay?<note place="margin">Biſhops Engliſh.</note> Now I pray you, reuerend brother, what is that? Whie Iacke doeſt thou not vnderſtand what our biſhoppes En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh meaneth? <hi>I</hi> doe not greatly maruell, becauſe
<pb facs="tcp:12606:13"/>
               <hi>I</hi> my ſelfe came but latelie vnto the knowledge of it aright. But nowe that <hi>I</hi> haue beſtowed a little ſtudie that waie, <hi>I</hi> doe thinke there are but a few in England, that ſee into it as farre as I doe, <hi>Semper excipio Platonem</hi> you know, <hi>I</hi> alwayes gine place to my father, for he made the firſt grammar and lexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con in our time for the vnderſtanding hereof. Thy ſmall experience then conſidered, <hi>I</hi> wonder not of thine ignorance in this poynt. But to ſatisfie thy demaunde, the biſhops Engliſh is to wreſt our lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage in ſuch ſorte, as they will drawe a meaning out of our Engliſh wordes, which the nature of the tougue can by no meanes beare. As for example, <hi>Receiue the Holy-Ghoſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">I am ſure, that they woulde not for forty pence, that, Receiue a biſhopricke, ſhoulde be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded vnto, wiſh thou may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt receiue a biſhopricke when they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the Holie-Ghoſt.</note> in good biſhops Engliſh is as much as, <hi>J pray God thou mayeſt receiue the Holy-ghoſt.</hi> And againe, <hi>My deſire is, that J may be baptized in this faith,</hi> to their vnderſtanding, and in their dialect is after this ſort; <hi>My deſire is, not that J my ſelfe, but that this childe vvherevnto J am a vvitneſſe, may bee baptized in this ſaith.</hi> Further to intreate her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie, and the Parliament, that the miſeries of the church may be redreſſed, in the Prelates language is, to ſeeke the ouerthrowe of the ſtate, and the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietneſſe of her ſubjects. And if a man ſhoulde goe and aske thine vncle Canturburie: (but ſtay boy, <hi>I</hi> meane not that thou ſhouldeſt goe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde the queſtion of him) what it were in the tongue, which he and his brethren doe commonly vſe, to put vp ſuch a dutifull ſupplication as before I haue ſet downe, why his anſwere woulde be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently, that to deale in ſuch a ſuire, were to rebell againſt her Majeſtie, to pull the crowne off of her head, to make a faction to wreſt the ſcepter out of her hand, and to ſhake off all authoritie. A won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull
<pb facs="tcp:12606:13"/>thing in thy conceit I knowe it will bee, to thinke, that humbly and duetifullie to entreate, ſhoulde in the Engliſh tongue ſignifie by vnbride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led force vnduetifullie to compell, and that to ſeeke the remoouing of vnlawefull callings out of the church ſhould be to threaten, that the lawfull magiſtrate ſhould bee thruſt out of the common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth: but, ſimple boy, ſuch Engliſh muſt thou ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to vnderſtand, or elſe thou ſhalt neuer be able to Piſtle thine vncle Canturburie ſo learned lie as my father and I can doe. And therefore I woulde wiſh, that of the firſt money, which thou meaneſt to beſtowe in bookes, thou wouldeſt buie thee thy fathers<note n="a" place="margin">Theſe bookes act not yet prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> Grammar and his lexicon, with a briefe thing called his <hi>capita concerdantiarum,</hi> and ſtudie theſe well but one moneth, and out o doubt, thou ſhalt, with the pretie skill which thou haſt already, be able to ouerturne anie catercap of them all. I would thou kneweſt what great light to the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of all the biſhops treacheries a little time beſtowed in theſe volumes haue affoorded vnto me.</p>
            <p>Wel, by this time I thinke thou perceiueſt what a braue waie this ſupplication which I ſpeake of, were, to prooue our biſhops to be treacherous and vile ſlaunderers. For hereby her Majeſtie ſhould perceiue, that the rumors which the biſhops raiſe falſly, concerning the great daunger that woulde enſue vnto her crowne, by the reformation which the Puritanes ſeeke and labor for, are nothing els, but in a cunning and myſticall kind of vnnaturall Engliſh to tranſlate, <hi>The Puritanes by the establishing of the kingdome of Chriſt, ſeeke the ſure vpholding of the crovvne and dignitie of their dread ſoueraigne ladie Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:12606:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>into this handſome biſhoplike miter: <hi>The Puritanes by their platforme of reformation ſeeke the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ruine and ſubuerſion of Ladie Elizabeth, her Crovvne and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gnitie.</hi> I am ſure her Majeſtie woulde welfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouredlie laugh at ſuch a tranſlation as this is, and yet beholde, ſuch ſhe muſt be content with, if ſhee will vouchſafe to yeelde her eares vnto a biſhops perſwaſion. Yet thus much muſt I ſay of them, namelie, that although they bee not the beſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounders of wordes that euer I read, yet doe they neuer tranſlate anie thing <hi>everbo ad verbum,</hi> which by learned men is commended as an eſpecial ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue in a tranſlator. But O that I, as ſimple as I am might reade a lecture or twoo concerning this bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoplike tranſlation, if not before her Majeſtie, yet at the leaſt before ſome of her nobles, I woulde not doubt but to vnfolde ſuch a deale of ſtrange Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh (and yet the verie <hi>vernacula</hi> viz. the naturall mother tongue of our vnnaturall Prelates) as was neuer heard of in this land ſince the Saxons time.</p>
            <p>Here I knowe, that thou arte readie to enquire two points of mee for thine inſtruction; the one, how our Prelates can be prooued Antichriſtes by the church of England, the other, howe thou may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt come by thoſe bookes of my father before quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Well, thus <hi>I</hi> will brieflie aunſweare thee in both.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, Maiſter Tindall in the Preface of his booke called, The Obedience of a Chriſtian man pag. 102. prooueth them to bee Antichriſtes, in as much as in their doctrine, and their dooings, concerning nonreſidencie, they are directlie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Chriſt and his worde. I charge thee reade the place, becauſe at this time I am not at leiſure
<pb facs="tcp:12606:14"/>to ſet it downe; I can tell thee the reading of it wil be double woorth thy paines.</p>
            <p>My fathers bookes afore ſpoken of, are not in print, <hi>I</hi> confeſſe, I would they were. Yet it may be I could direct thee where to go, to haue mine. But bicauſe I meane yet further to puniſh thee for thy ſlippes in thy Piſtle, I will not doe thee that plea ſure. For now in deede it commeth into my mind, that thou haſt dealt fooliſhlie in two points, beſide all other thy fore-reckoned ouerſights.</p>
            <p>Firſt thou haſt hereby exaſperated againſt thy father and other poore men his well willers, not onely thy vncle Caiphas, but haſt ſet on the moſt of thine neames, to giue their aduiſe howe to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trap him and his fauourers. For tenne to one, but that Beelzebub of London will diſcharge the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuvants, to go to their buſines with this or the like madmonition.</p>
            <p>My Maſters, you muſt not ſleepe in this matter. The maintena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the peace of our church ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth now in your faithfulnes and care. They are deſperately ſet to ouerthrowe al. And by the maſſe I will be a purſuvant my ſelfe, rather then abide this tumult. And if I were, I trowe I would watch about Trauerſe his houſe in Milke ſtreete, who go in and out there, and I would know what they ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried vnder their cloakes too, euen anie of them al. There is Paget at Hounſlo, I beſhrewe my heart if I would ſhewe him anie ſuch fauour as my Lordes Grace heere doeth. They are naught, they are naught, all the packe of them, Ile truſt none of them all. There is Cartwright too at Warwicke, he hath got him ſuch a companie of diſciples, both of the worſhipful, and other of the poorer ſort, as we
<pb facs="tcp:12606:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>haue no cauſe to thanke him. Neuer tell me, that he is too graue to trouble himſelfe with Martins conceits. Tuſh, they will doe anie thing to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw vs, that they might haue our liuings anie o them all. I knowe what a good liuing is able to do with the beſt of vs all. Cartwright ſeekes the peace of our Church no otherwiſe then his platforme may ſtand. And you knowe, my Lord, that there is no biting to the olde ſnake. And I doe not ſee o my troth, but that Martins abetters may be worſe then himſelfe, and doe more miſchiefe. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore goe me to all their houſes, ſpare mee none of them, knights, gentlemen, and all. For I truſt the high commiſſion may go to anie knight, yea, or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble mans houſe in England. Therfore, my Lords, I woulde wiſh, that ſome continuall ſpie may be in all thoſe places which are moſt ſuſpected. And let him learne to be wiſe, to creepe into acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with ſome of the preciſer ſorte, and looke ſmoothlie for a time, vntill hee can execute his commiſſion.</p>
            <p>Lo yongman, do not you deſerue ſtripes, for fle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing on theſe blood-hounds in this fort? Let men looke to keep them in as good temper as poſſiblie they can, yet wil they haue<note n="a" place="margin">The mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt token of a mad dog.</note> a blacke tooth in their heads, do what we may. But yet I would haue born with all this, if thou haddeſt taken a little paines in ryming with Mar-Martin; that the cater-caps may knowe, howe the meaneſt of my fathers ſonnes is able to anſweare them, both at blunt and ſharpe. And for thy further inſtruction againſt an other time, heere is a ſample for thee of that, which in ſuch like caſes thou art to performe, if <hi>I</hi> or my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhould ſet thee a worke.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12606:15"/>
            <p>¶ The firſt riſing, generation, and origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall <hi>of Mar-Martin.</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>From Sarum came a gooſes egge,</l>
               <l>with ſpecks and ſpots bepatched,</l>
               <l>A prieſt of Lambeth coucht thereon:</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Mar-Martin en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendred of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turburie and Sarum.</note>thus was Mar-Martin hatched.</l>
               <l>Whence hath Mar-Martin all his wit,</l>
               <l>but from that egge of Sarum?</l>
               <l>The reſt coms all from great Sir Iohn,</l>
               <l>who rings vs all this larum.</l>
               <l>What can the cokatrice hatch vp,</l>
               <l>but ſerpent like himſelfe?</l>
               <l>What ſees the Ape within the glaſſe,</l>
               <l>but a deformed Elfe?</l>
               <l>Then muſt Mar-Martin haue ſome ſmell</l>
               <l>of forge or elſe of fire,</l>
               <l>A ſotte in wit, a beaſt in minde:</l>
               <l>for ſo was damine and fire.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Or elſe thou mighteſt haue requited him in this Epitaph thus:
<q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>If that Mar-Martin die the death, that to the dog is due,</l>
                     <l>Vpon his tomb engrane this verſe, &amp; you shal find it true:</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>He lies endiched here that from the ladder toppe</l>
                     <l>Did once bebleſſe the people thus, but first he kiſt the rope</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Mar-Martins au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricular confeſſion from the toppe of a giber.</note>Come neere, quoth he, take heede by me,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> loued to lie by ryming,</l>
               <l>Tis juſt you ſee, and doth agrece,</l>
               <l>that now I die by climing:</l>
               <l>What wretch but I, that vowed to lie,</l>
               <l>all falſhoode ſtill defending?</l>
               <l>Who may ſay fie? No beaſt but <hi>I.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>loe here you ſee my ending.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:12606:16"/>
               <l>I liued a wretch, <hi>I</hi> die the ſtretch,</l>
               <l>my daies and death agree:</l>
               <l>Whoſe life is blameful, his death is ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,</l>
               <l>be warnd ye rogues by mee.</l>
               <l>The juſteſt <hi>I</hi> hated, the godlieſt I rated,</l>
               <l>and thus <hi>I</hi> railed my fill:</l>
               <l>The good I deteſted, the beſt things I wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted,</l>
               <l>to ſerue mine owne beaſtlie will.</l>
               <l>Religion I lothed, my ſelfe <hi>I</hi> betrothed,</l>
               <l>to all the lewd ſnares of ſinne.</l>
               <l>Tis ſhame to ſaye more, take heede of a whore,</l>
               <l>her<note n="a" place="margin">Beleeue him then, but drinke not with him.</note> markes ſticke yet in my skinne.</l>
               <l>Aske you the cauſe? <hi>I</hi> ſpurnd at Gods laws,</l>
               <l>and hence comes all my wracke,</l>
               <l>Where ſhould he dwel, that feares not hel,</l>
               <l>but with the furies blacke?</l>
               <l>A beaſt that braues, a tongue that raues,</l>
               <l>wil God reuenge in ire.</l>
               <l>Then vengeance muſt (for God is iuſt)</l>
               <l>fall to Mar-Martins hire.</l>
               <l>My tongue in ribaudrie,</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Take example then my cleargie Chapleins, by this lamentable fall of your Mar-Martin.</note>My heart in villanie,</l>
               <l>My life in treacherie,</l>
               <l>Hath wrought me my fall.</l>
               <l>I ſtroue for the prelacie,</l>
               <l>And ſo ſhooke off honeſtie,</l>
               <l>O vile indignitie!</l>
               <l>Yet woulde this were all.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Loe youth; though <hi>I</hi> were loth to file my fingers with ſuch a brothell beaſt as this Mar-Martin is, yet becauſe thou diddeſt let him goe by thee (mee thought) halfe vnbranded, I was the willinger as thou ſeeſt, to giue him a wipe or twoo, which <hi>I</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue he wil neuer claw off with honeſtie while he
<pb facs="tcp:12606:16"/>liues. And I would wiſh him, with the reſt of the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, if they be wiſe, to take heede of my next Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle. Indeede <hi>I</hi> denie not, but thou haſt ſaid pretily to him, neither woulde <hi>I</hi> haue thee diſcouraged in thy good and honorable courſe againſt theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates. Neuertheles, <hi>I</hi> muze thou diddeſt let him go cleare away with his poperie of ſir Nicholas Prieſtes. Alſo, where like a good Catholike hee counſels vs (we thanke him) to ſay a rounde <hi>Pater noſter</hi> for Q. Elizabeth, <hi>I</hi> muze thou ſaidſt nothing to that, conſidering how much her Majeſtie is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden to him in that regarde. And much more had ſhee beene, if hee had added an <hi>Aue Marie</hi> to it: thoſe both together, with a peece of S. Iohns Goſpell about ones loines, woulde haue beene a principall receit for the collicke. But ſure nowe <hi>I</hi> thinke on it, he brought it in one lie but to make vp his ryme. And if you ſcanne it well, tis a pretie one, marke it well:
<q>O England novv ful often muſt thou Pater noſter ſay.</q>
            </p>
            <p>How ſayſt thou, haſt thou anie skil in Muſike? If thou haue, then <hi>I</hi> am ſure thou wilt confeſſe with mee, that this baſtarde pentamenter verſe hath a fine ſweete looſe at the latter ende, with a draught of Darbie ale. But what ſayeſt thou to it? Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther likeſt thou better of theſe Nicholas Prieſtes that can ſo amble away with the <hi>Pater noſter,</hi> or of that little prieſt of Surrey, who bade his maide in her extreamitie of ſickeneſſe ſay, <hi>Magnificat,</hi> ſay <hi>Magnificat?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well boy, to drawe to an ende, notwithſtanding thy ſmall defectes, perſwade thy ſelfe, that <hi>I</hi> loue thee: doubt not of that. And here before we part, take this one graue leſſon of thine elder brother:
<pb facs="tcp:12606:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>Be ſilent and cloſe, heare manie, conferre with few. And in this point doe as <hi>I</hi> doe; know not thy father though thou mayeſt. For <hi>I</hi> tell thee, if <hi>I</hi> ſhoulde meete him in the ſtreete, <hi>I</hi> woulde neuer aske him bleſſing: walke ſmoothely and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectly. and if anie ofter to talke with thee of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin, talke thou ſtraite of the voyage into Portugal, or of the happie death of the Duke of Guyſe, or ſome ſuch accident; but meddle not with thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Onely, if thou haue gathered anie thing in viſitation for thy father, and haſt a longing to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint him therewith, doe no more but intreate him to ſignifie in ſome ſecret printed Piſtle where a will haue it lefte, and thatle ſerue thy turne as good as the beſt. The reaſon whie wee muſt not knowe our father is, that <hi>I</hi> feare leaſt ſome of vs ſhoulde fall into Iohn Canturburie his hand, and then heele threaten vs with the racke vnleſſe wee bewray all we knowe. And what get we then by our knowledge? For <hi>I</hi> had rather be ignorant or <hi>Thatle</hi> do me no good, then know <hi>Thatle</hi> hurt me, ka M. Martin Senior. Farewell boy, and learne to reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence thy elder brother.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>Pag. 6. line 18. for, giue all the good, reade, go all the ground</p>
            <p>Pag. 14. line 12. for, auoiding, reade vrging</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12606:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
